we all want to live life to the fullest
and longest right well this video will
look at the lifestyle factors that may
enable us to do just that check it out
[Music]
a pivotal paper published in europe more
than a decade ago entitled healthy
living is the best revenge
found that adhering to just four simple
healthy lifestyle factors compared to
none could potentially have a strong
impact on the prevention of chronic
diseases we're talking nearly 80 percent
less chronic disease risk slashing
diabetes risk by 93 dropping heart
attack risk by 81 and cutting stroke
risk in half and cancer by 36
think about what that means
the potential for preventing disease and
death is enormous in the us alone every
year there are a half million heart
attacks
half a million strokes a million new
cases of diabetes and a million new
cancer diagnoses
the message is clear adopting a few
healthy behaviors can have a major
impact
what are those four fabled factors never
smoking
not being obese averaging about a half
hour of exercise a day and adhering to
healthy dietary principles like lots of
fruits vegetables and whole grains and
less meat
follow those four simple rules and boom
enjoy nearly 80 percent reduced risk of
major chronic diseases what does that
mean for mortality risk
a similar batch of four healthy
behaviors combined predicted a four-fold
difference in total mortality with an
estimated impact equivalent to 14 years
in chronological age meaning the
individuals were dying at such a reduced
rate
that it was as if they were 14 years
younger
finally our regiment to extend human
life expectancy
this commentary was in reference to this
study where a similar analysis of the
impact of healthy lifestyle behaviors on
life expectancies was made but this time
it looked directly at the u.s population
which is particularly important since
americans have a shorter life expectancy
compared with residents of nearly all
other high-income countries the
researchers concluded that adopting a
healthy lifestyle could substantially
reduce premature mortality and prolong
life expectancy in u.s adults
okay but by how much they estimate that
adherence to a low-risk lifestyle could
prolong life expectancy at age 50 by 14
years in women and 12.2 years in men so
if you're 50 right now instead of only
living to 79 if you're a woman in 75 and
a half if you're a man
taking just basic care of yourself could
propel you to an average life expectancy
of 93 if you're a woman in 87 and a half
if you're a man
the bottom line is it's never too late
to turn back the clock a midlife switch
just to the basics like at least five
servings of fruits and vegetables a day
walking even like 20 minutes a day
maintaining a healthy weight and not
smoking results in a substantial
reduction mortality even in the
following few years we're talking a 40
lower risk of dying in the subsequent
four years so making the necessary
changes to adhere to a healthy lifestyle
could be considered extremely worthwhile
and middle age is certainly not too late
to act
as an aside realizing the 12 to 14 years
of added life study was based on data
from health professionals that got me
excited about all the potential knock-on
effects if health professionals start
getting healthier
they could become role models for more
healthful living and potentially save
more lives than just their own
but that may have just been wishful
thinking
practicing what you preach can sometimes
backfire evidently displays of
excellence can
paradoxically turn off
the very people you're trying to inspire
i mean you'd assume that not being a
hypocrite and trying to walk the walk
would just lead to positive consequences
inspiring confidence in others right
don't you want a dance instructor who
can dance a music teacher who can play a
health professional who's healthy
but this simple intuition fails to take
into account concerns about making other
people feel inadequate
like you know vegetarians are the
targets of a surprising amount of
hostility and ridicule that's because
they may come off as morally superior
and make people feel like they're being
looked down upon there was an elegant
demonstration this phenomenon in this
study where principal deviants who take
the high road threaten others moral
self-worth
this is what they did research subjects
were asked to complete a racist task by
an experimenter and those moral rebels
who refused to obey were cheered by
observers but were
disparaged by participants who had
themselves gone through with it and for
whom the rebel stance
thus implied an indictment of their
spinelessness isn't that interesting so
when doctors portray themselves as the
picture of health patients might think
they're being holier than thou and
unintentionally alienate people
potentially turning off the very
patients who most need their help
you can see how someone with a weight
issue might feel threatened and judged
by a physician triathlete
but what are we supposed to do we want
healthy practitioners physicians who
smoke are less likely to tell their
patients to quit smoking physicians who
are overweight are less likely to
counsel their patients about weight and
physicians who don't work out are less
likely to talk about exercise
what we can do
to make patients more comfortable is
emphasize that our role is to help
people meet their own
personal health goals whatever they may
be
studies show that when doctors do this
take this approach it increases the
appeal of fitness fitness-focused
physicians to overweight patients so we
can then display exemplary behavior
while at the same time not inadvertently
alienate the very people who could
benefit most from our guidance
[Music]
you